A Guide to the The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1813-1904, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts
  - Warrant pursuant to the complaint of Mary Harris against Nathaniel Clark, signed by John Hawthorne, Justice of the Peace, 1707/8 February 3, MDS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:48)
    For carnal knowledge and fathering her child out of wedlock, with Hawthorne's annotations on the verso recording the subsequent appearance of Clark and determination of his fine, 1707/8 February 14. #6249-a.
  - Account sheet, signed, N[athaniel] Hawthorne, for goods received of Willm. Manning and sold in Calcutta, docketed on the verso, 1800, MDS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:49)
    Business record, probably that of author Nathaniel Hawthorne's father. #6249-d.
  - Photostatic copies of letters and documents: 7 Nathaniel Hawthorne letters to various Hawthorne and Manning family members; 2 N.H. letters to others (Franklin Pierce and N.J. Lord); 6 letters to N.H. from Ralph Waldo Emerson, Grace Greenwood, Theodore Parker, James K. Paulding, Henry D. Thoreau, and his aunt Susan D. Manning; 5 letters from and to other family members (3 on the verso of N.H. letters); 2 documents signed by N.H., and 1 clipped N.H. signature;, 1821-1853, 20 ALsS, 2 MSDsS, and 1 clipped signature in 20 photostatic copies (some folded) of originals at the Essex Institute, Salem, Massachusetts; with two letters (1957) about these papers, one a photostatic copy (1 p.) and the other a TLS (2 pp.). (Box-folder 3:50)
    Regarding family matters, business, and other subjects. #6249-a.
  - Typescript copies of Nathaniel Hawthorne letters to various recipients, 1842-64, and 1 typescript copy of a letter from Herman Melville to N.H., 17 July [1852], 51 letters in typescript on 62 leaves; with a TLS (1 p.) from Norman Holmes Pearson to Waller Barrett (1959) accompanying these copies of letters in his collection and with a list (1 p.) of other N.H. related items in his possession. (Box-folder 3:51)
    Letters concerning his writing, consular duties, family matters, etc. #6249-d.
  - Customs house receipt, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, Surv, (and signed by other officials), for the Customs District of Salem and Beverly, 1846 November 1, DS, partially printed and completed in manuscript, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:52)
    #6249-d.
  - Customs house receipts, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, Surveyor (or Surv), and signed by other officials, for the Customs District of Salem and Beverly, 8 pieces, 1847 January 20 to 1848 June 2, 2 MDsS & 6 DsS, partially printed and completed in manuscript, each 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:53)
  - Customs house receipt, partially printed and completed in manuscript, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, Surv, and signed by other officials, 1848 September 26, 1 p. on 1 l.; with a manuscript note about it, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:54)
  - Receipt for payment of salary, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, Surveyor, for the Customs District of Salem and Beverly, 1848 October 1, MDS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:55)
  - Consular affidavits, signed N[athanie]l Hawthorne, as United States consul in Liverpool, England, 1854 February 17, 1854 February 17 (Box-folder 3:56)
    2 DsS, partially printed and completed in manuscript, each 1 p. on 1 l. #6249-a.
  - Consular certification on behalf of an injured seaman, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, as United States consul to Liverpool, 1854 October 19, MDS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:57)
    Written in a secretarial hand, describes his support of an American seaman injured in service, hospitalized, and being provided passage back to America. #6249-a.
  - Shipping certificate, signed Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, as United States consul to Liverpool, 1854 December 20, DS, partially printed and completed in manuscript, 2 pp. on 1 l., with a photostatic copy, 2 pp. (Box-folder 3:58)
  - Royalty check signed W.D. Ticknor & Co. and endorsed by Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1860 December 10, DS, partially printed and completed in manuscript, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:59)
  - Fragment from a letter, docketed by Nath[anie]l Hawthorne, n.y. October 1, 2 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:60)
    Identifies correspondence no longer attached or accompanying: "Mr. [John Louis?] O'Sullivan [to?, &?] Nathl Hawthorne of Salem [several words illegible] Oct 1st Copy of answer enclosed". On the verso in another hand is written, "Nathl Hawthorne. Salem", perhaps the address, which suggests that it dates from the years 1845 to 1849, and certainly well before 1864. #6249-a.
  - Unsigned note on Alexander Strahan, Publisher, letterhead, referring to a Nathaniel Hawthorne autograph, 1869 October 20, MN, 1 p. on 1 l. folded, with photostatic copy, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:61)
    Refers to once-accompanying gifts from "A Strahan" to the autograph collection of Miss McDonald, and promises that more will be sent "including notes from Victor Hugo, Carlyle, Hawthorne, and George Eliot". #6249-a.
  - Nathaniel Hawthorne: Tributes by American Authors on the 100th Anniversary of His Birth; Letters and brief manuscripts by American authors, replying to a request from Ralph Waldo Stoddard for remarks in tribute to Nathaniel Hawthorne for the centennial of his birth, 1904, Slipcase. Variously ALsS, TLsS, and MSsS, mounted individually on tabs in a black pebble-grained leather-bound notebook, housed in a blue cloth case (shelved separately). (Box-folder 3:62)
    The authors (listed in an accompanying manuscript index, which contains some errors): Henry Abbey, Oscar Fay Adams, John Albee, Azel Ames, E. Benjamin Andrews, William Loring Andrews, O.C. Auringer, Henry Carey Baird, Herbert Howe Bancroft, James Newton Baskett, Katharine Lee Bates, S.G.W. Benjamin, Poultney Bigelow, George S. Boutwell, Amory H. Bradford, Augusta Cooper Bristol, Theron Brown, James Buckham, Richard Burton, W.V. Byars, S.H.M. Byers, Madison J. Cawein, John Vance Cheney, Charles W. Chesnutt, Florence Earle Coates, Russell H. Conwell, Charles H. Crandall, Theodore S. Cuyler, Ellen Douglas Deland, Margaret Deland, Theodore L. DeVinne, P. Deming, Julia C.R. Dorr, Amanda M. Douglas, W.C. Doane, Charles F. Dole, Nathan Haskell Dole, Edward S. Ellis, W.D. Ellwanger, Edward W. Emerson, W.H.P. Faunce, Sidney G. Fisher, Alcée Fortier, Mary E. Wilkins Freeman, Eliot Gregory, George McLean Harper, Albert Bushnell Hart, Ella Higginson, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Charles F. Holder, Mary J. Holmes, Oliver Otis Howard, Ernest Ingersoll, Joseph Jacobs, Adrian H. Joline, Charles Keeler, James B. Kenyan, Ellen Olney Kirk, Frederic Lawrence Knowles, M. Alphonsa Lathrop [Rose Hawthorne Lathrop after becoming a Catholic nun], John Uri Lloyd, John Luther Long, Thomas R. Lounsbury, Ernest McGaffey, Edgar S. Maclay, F. Schuyler Mathews, Frederick A. Ober, Samuel T. Pickard, Lizette Woodworth Reese, Agnes Repplier, Eben E. Rexford, Charles F. Richardson, William H. Rideing, Clinton Ross, F.B. Sanborn, George Santayana, Clinton Scollard, A.R. Spofford, Charles Warren Stoddard, Josiah Strong, Rose Hartwick Thorpe, Oscar L. Triggs, Clarence T. Urmy, Charles Henry Webb, Ella Wheeler Wilcox, Benjamin J. Wheeler. #6249-d.
  - Biographical notes and excerpts from books, all concerning Una Hawthorne, compiler unidentified, n.y. (but 1955 or later, based on internal evidence), Typed transcripts with scattered manuscript corrections, 47 pp. on 47 leaves. (Box-folder 3:63)
    Excerpts include notes about sources; unascribed piece refers to a letter dating from 1855 as being a century old. #6249-a.
  - Description of Nathaniel Hawthorne's manuscript for A Wonder Book for Girls and Boys, excerpt from the chapter, Textual Introduction, in A Wonder Book and Tanglewood Tales, volume 7 in the Centenary Edition of the Works of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1972, Photocopy, 15 pp. on 8 l. (Box-folder 3:64)
    Detailed description of the manuscript, which was examined in the Barrett Collection by editors preparing the Centenary Edition for publication. (The manuscript, subsequently gone missing, is preserved in photocopy and housed with the Barrett Hawthorne Papers.) #6249.
- Series IV: Photographs and Prints
  - Portrait of Nathaniel Hawthorne and view of the Old Manse, Concord, Massachusetts, n.d., 2 ambrotypes, both approximately 5.5 x 4.5 inches. (Oversize O.S. Box AA-10 cell L.)
    Portrait from later in his life, ca. 1860. #6249-d.
  - Photographic copies from ambrotypes, one of Nathaniel Hawthorne and one of his home, the Old Manse, Concord, Massachusetts, n.d., 2 black and white photographs, both approximately 9.5 x 12.5 inches (2 copies of each); with related correspondence, 2 pp. on 2 leaves. (Box-folder 4:1)
    Presented by Mrs. Barton W. Currie; originals also in the Barrett Collection (O.S. Box AA-10 cell L). Accompanied by correspondence about provenance. #6249-d.
  - Portrait photograph of Nathaniel Hawthorne, seated and holding a book, signed "Hawthorne," n.d., 1 carte de visite, 2.25 x 4 inches. (Box-folder 4:2)
    Backmarked Under the Superintendence of Mr. S.B. Heald, Warren's, 289 Washington Street, Boston, Mass. Likeness taken probably in the 1850s. #7053-a.
  - Portrait photograph of Nathaniel Hawthorne, seated in a chair and holding a book, a cabinet card, n.d., 1 cabinet card, 5.5 x 4 inches. (Box-folder 4:3)
    Likeness taken probably in the 1850s. #7053-a.
  - Portrait photograph of Nathaniel Hawthorne, seated in a chair beside a table and reading a book, n.d., 1 photograph, 3.25 x 2.25 inches. (Box-folder 4:4)
    Likeness taken probably in the 1850s. #7694-c.
  - Portrait photograph of Nathaniel Hawthorne, seated, wearing a coat and scarf and holding a hat, n.d., 1 photograph, 3.25 x 2.25 inches. (Box-folder 4:5)
    Reproduced from a carte de visite or cabinet card, photographer's name and Salem, Mass. faintly evident in the lower margin of the card; likeness taken probably in the 1850s. #7694-a.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, with signature facsimile, by H.B. Hall & Sons, n.d., 1 engraving mounted on stiff paper, 7.5 x 5.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:6)
    From a likeness taken probably in the 1850s. #6249-a.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by S[amuel] Hollyer, with signature facsimile, n.d., 1 engraving, on stiff paper 12.75 x 9.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:7)
    From a likeness taken probably in the 1850s. Engraving signed in pencil by the artist. #6249-d.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by T. Phillibrown, head and shoulders, with facsimile signature, n.d., 1 engraving, on paper 8 x 5.25 inches. (Box-folder 4:8)
    From a painting by C[ephas] G. Thompson (1850). #6249-b.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, head and shoulders, with facsimile signature, n.d., 1 engraving, on stiff paper 10.5 x 6.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:9)
    From an 1850 painting by Cephas Thompson. #6249-d.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, head and shoulders, with signature facsimile, reproduced on a postcard, n.d., 1 print, black and white, 5.5 x 3.5 inches, mounted on paper. (Box-folder 4:10)
    From an 1850 painting by Cephas Thompson. Reference Collection.
  - Portrait etching of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by S[tephen] A[lonzo] Schoff, n.d., 1 etching on thin paper 10.5 x 7.5 inches. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Portrait etching of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by S[tephen] A[lonzo] Schoff, n.d., 1 etching on paper 8 x 5 inches. (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne with facsimile signature, by J.A.J. Wilcox, n.d., 1 engraving, 7.5 x 5.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:13)
    Likeness taken later in his life. #6249-a.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by J.A.J. Wilcox, n.d., 1 engraving, 7.5 x 5 inches. (Box-folder 4:14)
    Likeness taken later in his life; without facsimile signature. #6249-a.
  - Portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne, by J.A.J. Wilcox, n.d., 1 photographic copy, 8 x 10 inches. (Box-folder 4:15)
    Likeness taken later in his life. #6526-k.
  - Print after portrait engraving of Nathaniel Hawthorne by J.A.J. Wilcox, n.d., 1 print in brown ink, 5 x 3.5 inches on leaf 8.5 x 5.5 inches. (Box-folder 4:16)
    Likeness taken later in his life (stain affecting image). Reference Collection.
  - Photographic portrait of An American Immortal, Nathaniel Hawthorne, clipped illustration from a book or magazine, n.d., 1 print, black and white and gold, oval 2.5 x 2 inches, mounted on paper. (Box-folder 4:17)
    Likeness taken later in his life. Reference Collection.
  - Nathaniel Hawthorne, see Irving, Washington: Print, coloured, by George E. Perine, entitled Washington Irving and His Literary Friends at Sunnyside (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Signature Nathl Hawthorne,n.d., 1 photographic enlargement, 4 x 10 inches. (Box-folder 4:19)
    #7053-a.
  - Engraving, Residence of Nathl. Hawthorne, Concord, Mass, drawn by W.R. Miller, engraved by J.D. Duthie, published by G.P. Putnam & Co., n.d., 1 engraving, on paper 8.5 x 5.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:20)
    View of The Wayside. #6249-b.
  - [Hawthorne], Sophia [Amelia Peabody], Drawing: Socrates, about to Drink the Hemlock, Takes Leave of His Disciples,n.d., 1 pencil drawing, on Bristol board 7.25 x 12.25 inches, captioned, ribbon tie threaded through near top edge, with typed transcription identified as taken from a label on the back of a frame from which the drawing was removed. (Box-folder 4:21)
    Drawing bears a faint pencil caption and an ink annotation in another hand. Image after Antonio Canova's relief in the Villa Torlonia, Rome. #6663.
  - [Hawthorne, Sophia Amelia Peabody, attributed], Drawing of a rural view, n.d., 1 pencil drawing, on paper 6.25 x 3.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:22)
    Drawing of a riverside cottage, thatched outbuilding, and fence; annotated in pencil on the verso, "Found with some of Mrs. Nath. Hawthorn's [sic] Letters. R.W. Lul. Probably drawing by her or one of her daughters?" #6249-a.
  - [Hawthorne, Sophia Amelia Peabody, attributed to], No 2 / Aug 31, 1870, drawing of a cottage, 1870 August 31, 1 pencil drawing, on paper 6.25 x 3.75 inches. (Box-folder 4:23)
    Drawing of a cottage, annotated in pencil at the lower left corner with number and date. #6249-a.